<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles and ordinances of warre for the present expedition of the armie of the kingdome of Scotland. By his Excellence, the Lord Generall of the armie.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11664</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21914</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101501</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837315</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837315</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1631</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11664)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1631)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1394:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles and ordinances of warre for the present expedition of the armie of the kingdome of Scotland. By his Excellence, the Lord Generall of the armie.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Army.</author>
                  <author>Leven, Alexander Leslie, Earl of, 1580?-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by James Bryson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Lord Generall of the armie = Alexander Leslie, 1st Earl of Leven.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1631:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1631:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES <hi>AND</hi> ORDINANCES <hi>OF WARRE;</hi> For the preſent expedition of <hi>the Armie of the Kingdome</hi> of SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>BY HIS EXCELLENCE, the Lord Generall of the Armie.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>J.B.</p>
               <figDesc>printer's device of James Bryson</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>EDINBVRGH, Printed by <hi>James Bryſon,</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:1631:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:1631:2"/>
            <head>ARTICLES AND ordinances of VVarre, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT no man pretend igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;<note place="margin">The pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles andor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of warre.</note> and that every one may know the duetie of his place, that hee may doe it: The Articles and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces following, are to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed at the general randez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous in every regiment apart, by the Marſhals of the ſeverall Regiments, &amp; in the preſence of all the Officers. The ſame ſhall after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward be openly read to every Companie of Horſe and foot, and at ſuch times as ſhall be thought moſt convenient by the Lord Generall: and in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhall bee made knowne to ſo many as joyne themſelves to be profeſſed Souldiours in the Armie. For this end, every Colonell and Captaine ſhall provide one of thoſe Bookes, that hee may have it in readineſſe at all occaſions, and every Souldiour ſhall ſolemnely ſweare this following oath,</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The oath of Souldiours.</note>
               <hi>I N. N. promiſe and ſweare to be true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in my ſervice to the Kingdome of</hi> Scotland, <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the heads ſworne by me in the Covenant. To honour and obey my Lord Generall, and all my Superiour
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1631:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Officers and Commanders, and by all meanes to hinder their diſhonour and hurt: To obſerve carefully all the Articles of warre and Campe diſcipline: never to leave the defence of this Cauſe, nor ſlie from my Colours ſo long as I can follow them: To be ready to watching warding and working, ſo far as I have ſtrength: To en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure and ſuffer all diſtreſses, and to fight manfully to the uttermoſt, as I ſhall anſwere to GOD, and as GOD ſhall helpe mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. Kirk diſcipline ſhall be exerciſed, and the poore cared for in every Regiment,<note place="margin">Kirk diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline.</note> by the particular El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip, or Kirke Seſſion to be appointed, even as uſeth to bee done in every paroſh in the time of peace: And that there may bee an uniformitie throughout the whole Armie in all matters Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall; there ſhall bee a generall Elderſhip, or common Eccleſiaſticke judicatorie, made up of all the Miniſters of the Campe, and of one Elder direct from every particular Regiment, who ſhall alſo judge of appellations, made unto them from the particular Seſſions or Elderſhips.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Councels of w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>II. For deciding of all queſtions, debats and quarrellings, that ſhall ariſe betwixt Captaines and their Souldiours, or any others of the Armie, and for the better obſerving of Campe Diſcipline, two courts of Juſtice, the one higher and the other lower, are appointed, wherein all Judges are ſworne to doe Juſtice equally: The higher alſo to judge of appellations to bee made from the lower court. And if any man ſhall by word or geſture ſhow his contempt or miſ-regard, or ſhall fall out in boaſting or braving, while Courts are ſitting, hee ſhall bee puniſhed by death. And both theſe Judicatories as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1631:3"/>well of the Kirke matters as of warre, ſhall be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the councell of Eſtate, and generall Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <hi>reſpective.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">Dueties to God.</note>III. VVhoſoever ſhall wilfully or careleſly abſent himſelfe from morning and evening prayers, or from preaching before and after-noone on the Lords day, or other dayes of the weeke, when the ſigne is given by ſound of Trumpet, or Drum, hee ſhall bee cenſured and puniſhed for his neglect or contempt, by penaltie, impriſonment, or other puniſhment, as his fault deſerveth.</p>
            <p>After the warning given, there ſhall bee no Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, nor ſelling of commodities whatſoever, till the Prayers or Preaching be ended, upon the paine of fore-faulting the things ſo ſold, and of the impriſoning of the offenders.</p>
            <p n="4">IIII. Common and ordinarie ſwearing and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, open prophaning of the Lords day, wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Miniſters, and other acts of that kinde, ſhall not only bee puniſhed with loſſe of pay, and impriſonment, but the tranſgreſſours ſhall make their publicke repentance, in the midſt of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and if they vvill not bee reclaimed, they ſhall with diſgrace bee openly caſſeered, and diſcharged as unworthie of the meaneſt place in the Armie.</p>
            <p n="5">V. If any man ſhall open his mouth againſt the Kings Majeſties perſon, or Authoritie,<note place="margin">Duetie to King Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</note> or ſhall preſume to touch his ſacred Perſon, hee ſhall bee puniſhed as a traitour. Hee that ſhall ſpeake evil of the Cauſe which wee defend, or of the Kingdome and Countrey in the defence thereof, or ſhall uſe any words tending to the diſhonour of the Lord
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1631:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Generall, hee ſhall bee puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p>No man ſhall at his owne hand, without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of my Lord Generall, have or keepe intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence with the enemie, by ſpeach, letters, ſignes, or any other way, under the paine to bee puniſhed as a traitour. No man ſhall give over any Strength, Magazin, victuall, &amp;c. Or make any ſuch moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but upon extremitie, under the ſame paine. No man ſhall give ſupply, or furniſh money, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, or any commodities to the enemie, upon paine of death.</p>
            <p>VVhoſoever ſhall bee found to doe violence againſt the Lord Generall his Safe-guarde, or ſafe-conduct, ſhall die for it.</p>
            <p>VVhoſoever ſhall bee found guiltie of careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and negligence in his ſervice, although he be free of treacherie and double dealing, ſhall beare his owne puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. All Commanders and Officers ſhall bee carefull,<note place="margin">Dueties of Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours.</note> both by their authoritie and example, that all under their charge, live in godlines, ſoberneſſe, and righteouſneſſe: and if they themſelves ſhall be common ſwearers, curſers, drunkards, or any of them at any time, ſhall come drunke to his Guarde, or by quarrelling, or any other way ſhall commit any notable diſorder in his quarter, loſſe of place ſhall bee his puniſhment: And further, according to the ſentence of the court of warre.</p>
            <p>The Captaines that ſhall be negligent in training their Companies, or that ſhall bee found to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from their Souldiours any part of their pay, ſhall bee diſcharged of their place, and further cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the court of warre.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:1631:4"/>
            <p>No Commander or Officer ſhall conceal dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous &amp; diſcontented humours, inclined to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinies, or grudging at the orders given them, but ſhall make them knowne to the prime Leaders of the Armie, upon the paine to bee accounted guiltie of mutinie.</p>
            <p>No Commander or Officer ſhall authorize or wittingly permit any Souldiour to go forth to a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular combat, under paine of death; But on the contrarie, all Officers ſhall be carefull by all meanes to part quarrellings amongſt Souldiours, although they bee of other Regiments, or Companies, and ſhal have power to command them to priſon, which if the Souldiours ſhall diſobey or reſiſt by uſing any weapon, they ſhall die for it.</p>
            <p>No Captaine ſhall preſume at his owne hand, without warrant of the Lord Generall, to caſſeere or give a Paſſe to any enroled Souldiour, or Officer who hath appeared at the place of the generall Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvous; nor ſhall any Commander, Officer, or Souldiour depart without a Paſſe, or ſtay behinde the time appointed him in his Paſſe, and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver tranſgreſſeth the one way or the other, ſhall bee puniſhed at the diſcretion of the Court of Ware.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">Dueties of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours.</note>VII. All Souldiours ſhall remember that it is their part to honour and obey their Commanders and therefore ſhall receive their commands with reverence, and ſhall make no noyſe, but bee ſilent, when the Officers are commanding or giving their directions, that they may be heard by all, and the better obeyed he that faileth againſt this, ſhall bee impriſoned.</p>
            <p>No Souldiour ſhall leave his Captaine, nor ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1631:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>forſake his maſter, whether hee abyde in the Army or not; but upon licence granted and in an orderly way.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever ſhall preſume to diſcredit any of the great Officers of the armie, by writ, word, or any other way, and be not able to make it good, and whoſoever ſhall lift his weapon againſt any of them ſhall be puniſhed by death; and whoſoever ſhall lift his hand againſt any of them, ſhall loſſe his hand.</p>
            <p>No Souldiour nor inferior officer ſhall quarrell with, or offer any injurie to his Superiour, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe any duety commanded him upon paine of caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeering, and to be further cenſured by the court of warre. And if any ſhall preſume to ſtrike his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, hee ſhall bee puniſhed with death. But if it ſhall happen that any Officer ſhall command any thing to the evident and known prejudice of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick, then ſhall hee who is commanded modeſtly refuſe to obey, and preſently give notice therof to the Lord Generall.</p>
            <p>If any man ſhall uſe any words or wayes, tending to mutinie or ſedition, whither for demanding his pay, or upon any other cauſe, or if any man ſhall bee privie to ſuch mutinous ſpeaches, or wayes, and ſhall conceal them; both ſhall bee puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p>All muſt ſhow their valour againſt the enemie, and not by revenging their private injuries, which upon their complaints to their ſuperiour Officers, ſhall be repared to the full. And if any man preſume to take his owne ſatisfaction, or challenge a combat, hee ſhall bee impriſoned, and have his puniſhment de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by the marſhall court.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:1631:5"/>
            <p>The Provoſt marſhall muſt not bee reſiſted, or hindred in apprehending, or putting delinquents in priſon, and all Officers muſt aſſiſt him to this end, and if any man ſhall reſiſt or breake priſon, he ſhall be cenſured by the court of warre.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <note place="margin">Dueties to others.</note>VIII. Murther is no leſſe unlawfull and intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in the time of warre, then in the time of peace, and is to bee puniſhed with death.</p>
            <p>VVhoſoever ſhall bee found to have forced any woman, whither hee bee Commander or Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, ſhall die for it without mercie. And whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall bee found guiltie of adulterie or fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhall bee no leſſe ſeverly cenſured and puniſhed then in the time of peace.</p>
            <p>Theeves and robbers ſhall be puniſhed with the like ſeverity. If any ſhall ſpoile, or take any part of their goods that die in the Armie, or are killed in ſervice he ſhall reſtore the double and be farther pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at diſcretion. It is provyded that all their goods be foorth comming and be diſpoſed of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their teſtament, &amp; will declared by word or writ before witneſſes, or if they have made no teſtament, to their wives, children, or neareſt kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, according to the lawes of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>All ſhall live together as friends and brethren, abſtaining from words of diſgrace, contempt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, giving of lies, and all provocation by word or geſture: Hee that faileth, ſhall bee impriſoned for the firſt fault, and if hee bee incorrigible, hee ſhall bee with ſhame put out of the Armie.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning armes.</note>IX. All Souldiours ſhall come to their Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, to watch, to be exerciſed, or to muſter, with their owne Armes, and if any Souldiour ſhall come
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1631:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>with another mans Armes, hee ſhall bee puniſhed with rigour, and the lender ſhall loſſe his Armes. All ſhall come alſo with compleat and tight Armes in a decent maner, otherwiſe to be ſeverly puniſhed.</p>
            <p>If any man ſhall ſell, or give in pawne his horſe, his armes, or any part of the ammunition comitted to him, or any inſtruments, as Spades, Shovels, Pickes uſed in the field, hee ſhall for the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time bee beaten, through the quarter, and for the third time bee puniſhed as for other thift: And hee that buyeth them, or taketh them to pawne, be hee Souldiour, or Victualler, ſhall pay the double of the money, beſide the want of the things bought or impawned, and be further puniſhed at diſcretion.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever in a debauched and leud manner by Cards or Dyce, or by ſloath, and unexcuſable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect, ſhall loſſe his horſe, and armes in whole, or in part to the hinderance of the ſervice; And whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall wilfully ſpoile, or breake his Armes, or any inſtrument of warre committed to him, by cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe of trees, or any other way, hee ſhall ſerve as a pioner, till the loſſe be made up, and he furniſhed upon his owne charges.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <note place="margin">Concerning marching.</note>X. No man on his march, or at his lodging within or without the countrey upon whatſoever pretext, ſhall take by violence either horſe, cattell, goods, money, or any other thing, leſſe, or more, but ſhall pay the uſuall pryces for his meat and drinke, or bee furniſhed according to the order gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Lord Generall upon paine of death, without mercie.</p>
            <p>If any man ſhall preſume to pull down, or ſet on fire any dwelling houſe, though a Cottage, or hew
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1631:6"/>downe any fruite-trees, or to waſte, or deface any part of the beautie of the countrey, hee ſhall bee puniſhed moſt ſeverly, according to the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the fault.</p>
            <p>In marching, no man ſhall ſtay behinde without leave: No man ſhall ſtraggle from his Troup or Companie. No man ſhall march out of his ranke, and put others out of order, under all higheſt paine.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <note place="margin">Of muſters</note>XI. If any Colonell of horſe or foot ſhall keepe back his Souldiours from the appointed muſters, or shall lend his Souldiours to make a falſe muſter, upon tryal in the court Marshal, he ſhalbe punished as a deceiver. And if any Muſter-maſter shall uſe any falſe Rols, shall have any hand in falſe Muſters, or by connivence, or any other way be tryed, to be acceſſory to them, he shal ſuffer the like punishme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <note place="margin">Victuallers.</note>XII. No man shall preſume to doe the ſmalleſt injurie to any that bring neceſſaries to the Leager, whither by ſtealing from them, or deceiving them, or by violence in taking their horſe or goods, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the paine to be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; punished asenemies. No Victualler shal ſell rotten victuals, upon pain of impriſonment and confiſcation, and futher as they shall bee judged to deſerve.</p>
            <p>No Souldiour shall provide and ſell Victuals, unleſſe he be authorized, nor shall any that ſelleth Victuals, keepe in his Tent or Hutte, any Souldiour at unſeaſonable houres, and forbiden times, under paine at diſcretion, Like-as, all the pryces thereof shall be ſet down by the generall Marshall, and be given to the Marshall of the ſeverall Regiments.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <note place="margin">Dueties in the Campe.</note>XIII. No man enrolled profeſſing himſelfe or pretending to be a ſouldiour ſhall abide in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1631:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Army, unleſſe he enter in ſome Company, nor ſhall he that hath entered depart without licence upon the paine of death. No man having licence ſhall ſtay beyond the time appointed him upon paine of loſſe of his pay during the time of his abſence, and further puniſhment at diſcretion. If any man in a mutinous way ſhow himſelf diſcontent with the quarter aſſigned him he ſhall be puniſhed as a mutiner. And if any man shall ſtay out of his quarter or goe without ſhot of cannon being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinshed, but one night, without leave of his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour officer he shall be caſſeerd.</p>
            <p>All that shall be abſent from the watch after the ſigne is given for the ſetting thereof shall be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely punished. He that revealeth or falſifieth the watchword given by the officer, within the trinches, or before the cullours: He that is taken ſleeping or drunken upon his watch: he that cometh off the watch before the tyme, every one of thoſe shall be punished with death.</p>
            <p>If any number of Souldiours shall aſſemble to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for taking mutinous counſell upon whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever pretext: The Officers joyning with them, shall ſuffer death: The tenth man of the Souldiours shall be hanged, and the reſt condemned to bee pioners, and to purge the Campe, till by ſome exploit they procure pardon, and redeeme their reputation.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <note place="margin">Dueties in Battell.</note>XIIII. Everie man when the Alarum is given, shall repaire ſpeedily to his Cullours; no man shall forſake or ſlee from his Cullours.</p>
            <p>No man in the countrey shall receit them that flee.</p>
            <p>No man in the Battell shall throw away his Mus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, Pick, or Bandileir, all under the paine of death.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:1631:7"/>
            <p>Whatſoever Regiment of horſe or foot, having charged the enemie, ſhall draw backe, before they come to ſtroke of ſword, ſhall anſwer for it before a councel of war: And if it be through default of any Officer, hee ſhall bee cenſured by the Councel of warre. If the fault be in the Souldiours, the tenth man ſhall bee puniſhed with death, and the reſt put to baſe ſervice, till by their valour they prove themſelves worthie of a better condition.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <note place="margin">Dueties after Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell.</note>XV. If it shall come to paſſe, that the enemie shall force us to Battell, and the Lord shall give us victorie, none shall kill a yeelding enemie, nor ſave him that ſtill purſueth, upon paine of death. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall there be any ranſoming of perſons, ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, pillaging, parting of the prey, or waſting and burning by fire, or disbanding from their charges, or Officers, but as the Lord Generall ſhall give or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon the ſame paine of death.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <note place="margin">Rewards for the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerving.</note>XVI. Every mans carriage shall bee diligently obſerved, and hee according to his merite reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or punished: And whatſoever Officer or Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour shall carrie himſelfe duetifully in his ſtation, and doth his part valiantly, in Battell or fight, shall after the laudable example of the wiſeſt, and worthieſt Kingdomes and Eſtates, have his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reward according to his worth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, whither hereafter we have peace or warre.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matters that are cleareby the light and law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are preſuppoſed: Things unneceſſarie, are paſt over in ſilence: and other things may be judged by the common cuſtomes and conſtitutions of warre, or may upon new emergents, bee expreſſed afterward.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
